James Scott Sheppard

jssheppard83@gmail.com 636-288-3325 GitHub LinkedIn

Summary

Recently, I completed the nationally recognized LaunchCode Discovery and LC101 coding programs. The LaunchCode organization nurtured my foundational skills of coding, programming, software, and web development. This has been my most challenging and rewarding educational program.

I am motivated to grow my career in software and web development, and to apply my abilities in computer programming, team collaboration, leadership, time management, adaptability, and project management.

Skills

Programming Languages include: Python, C#, Java, JavaScript, HTML5, CSS, MySQL, and Visual Basic.

Frameworks and Platforms include: Razor, Flask, Django, Bootstrap, Angular, and WordPress.

Software includes: Visual Studio Code, IntelliJ, Notepad ++, GitHub, MySQL Workbench, Android Studio, and Microsoft Office 365.

Object-oriented skills and principles: Defining Classes and Creating Objects, Class Inheritance, Polymorphism, Interfaces 3, and Access Modifiers.

ASP.NET MVC Multi-featured web applications: Create and configure controllers, persistent model classes via ADO.NET, Create views using Razor templates.

Projects

https://github.com/james636

Blogz Project

- Built project using Python3, Flask, and Jinja2 for the routing, templates, and controllers.
- The project included persist data in a MySQL database, retrieving the data for display (Flask-SQLalchemy), added authentication for login to create posts, and limiting access to visitors without accounts. For database security, I added password hashing and salting.
- This project was an addition to Build-a-Blog project. Refactoring to expand my codebase making this a multi-user blog site.
- This project features different user scenarios. Required login, verification, CRUD database, and log
 out. Logged-in users, can create new posts, sort, delete, and modify. Not logged-in users are
 directed to login page and can also view a display of default sort.

CHEESE MVC Persistence Project

- Project includes a multi-platform C# console project that uses EFCore and SQLite on Visual Studio.
- The Web Application creates many-to-many relationships with several models, controllers and views, allowing the user to add/remove, via the Web Form, menus, categories, and types of cheeses.
- The project focused on persistent model classes, OOP, and views using Razor templates.

Education

2018-2019 LaunchCode Discovery and LC101 Certificates

LaunchCode, St. Louis, MO

- Coding courses designed to prepare participants as software and web developers with a focus on Object Oriented Programming (OOP) analysis and methods.
- The courses focused on several programming languages including: Python, Java, C#, JavaScript, HTML, CSS, and Bootstrap framework.
- Strong emphasis on Agile Software development methods.
- Program and Software projects developed with LaunchCode can be found on my <u>GitHub</u> and <u>LinkedIn</u>.

2004-2007 Pre-Law/Political Science, Bachelor's Degree

University of Missouri, St. Louis, MO

- Earned 3.73 GPA during two years of College education.
- Recognized by Dean of College for excellent academic performance.

2002-2004 Business Administration, Associate's Degree

St. Charles Community College, St Charles, MO

Awarded a Degree of High Honors.

Experience

2014-2018 Admissions Coordinator

Vatterott College, St Louis, MO

- Serve as the initial contact to advise and assist prospective students and their parents in the understanding of academic programs and admissions requirements.
- Troubleshoot any student technical issues with Docusign and Adobe Sign
- Build and maintain contact information through CampusVue, Outlook, CityGro, BoldChat, and Setster Appointment.
- Highly independent effort with success from customer service/support while coordinating with team of Admissions for enrollment success.
- Informational liaison between Admissions, Financial Aid, Career Services, Retention, Academic Director, and Accounting departments.

2010-2014 General Manager

Cash America International, St Louis, MO

- Managed Loan and Pawn Services, including loan interest calculations and collections of accounts on past due and delinquent loans.
- Drove Storefront Operations opening/closing and audit preparation.
- Oversaw accounting and invoicing for accurate deposits and monthly profit statements. Monthly, Quarterly, Yearly sales meetings and budgets with regional management.

2006-2010 Assistant Manager

Wal-Mart Stores Inc., St Louis, MO

- Provided supervision and development for 350 hourly Associates and Supervisors: hiring, training, mentoring, assigning duties, evaluating performance, providing recognition, and ensuring diversity awareness.
- Implemented new Inventory Management System for fresh food products and general merchandise, resulting in decreased overhead and added productivity for inventory team.
- Managed a high volume Supercenter of \$100 million in annual sales.